<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Shale Network</title>
<link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/</link>
<atom:link href="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>2022 Shale Network Workshop</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2022-shale-network-workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Ten Years of Unconventional Resource Development: Lessons Learned and Future Directions</strong></p>
<p><strong>Date:</strong></p>
<p>May 12–13, 2022</p>
<p><strong>Location:</strong></p>
<p>The Graduate State College, 125 S Atherton St, State College, PA 16801</p>
<p><strong>Workshop Organized and/or Sponsored By:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>National Science Foundation, Penn State (Earth and Environmental Systems Institute; Marcellus Center for Outreach and Research)</p></li>
<li><p>University of Pittsburgh</p></li>
<li><p>Syracuse University</p></li>
<li><p>Evergreen Conservancy</p></li>
<li><p>PA Department of Environmental Protection (PA DEP)</p></li>
<li><p>Seneca Resources</p></li>
<li><p>Oak Ridge Associated Universities_</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2022 Shale Network Workshop Agenda</strong></p>
<p><a href="2022-shale-network-workshop/Agenda.pdf">2022 Shale Network Workshop Agenda PDF</a></p>
<p><a href="2022-shale-network-workshop/AbstractHandout.pdf">View the 2022 Shale Network Workshop Abstracts</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Workshop</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2022-shale-network-workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2021 Shale Network Workshop</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2021-shale-network-workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Registration for the ninth annual Shale Network Workshop is now open. The theme of the 2021 workshop is “Shale Gas: Future and Developing Issues” and includes presentations on the health effects related to shale gas development by Donna Vorhees, director of energy research at the Health Effects Institute, and Joan Casey, assistant professor of environmental health sciences at Columbia University. The workshop will be held virtually on May 13-14.</p>
<p>The workshop provides an opportunity for citizen scientists, researchers, government officials, energy company representatives, and environmental professionals to compare lessons learned about water and environmental issues within areas where shale energy development is occurring.</p>
<p>The 2021 workshop features two <strong>virtual</strong> field trips - one to a shale gas development site and the other to a solar farm. Workshop participants may attend both field trips; advanced registration is required.</p>
<p><strong>This year’s virtual talks will not be recorded, but if speakers wish to share their slides, Shale Network will make the presentations available after the workshop.</strong></p>
<p>Shale Network is a collaborative effort between Penn State, Syracuse University, and the University of Pittsburgh to collect and analyze data on water quality in the Marcellus Shale drilling region. The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection participates in organizing parts of the workshop.</p>
<p><a href="2021-shale-network-workshop/How_to_Zoom-Participants-final.pdf"><strong>Zoom Instructions for Participants</strong></a></p>
<p><a href="2021-shale-network-workshop/How_to_Zoom-Panelists_and_Speakers.pdf"><strong>Zoom Instructions for Panelists and Speakers</strong></a>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>2021 Shale Network Workshop Agenda</strong></p>
<p><a href="2021-shale-network-workshop/2021_Shale_Network_Workshop_Agenda.pdf">2021 Shale Network Workshop Agenda PDF</a></p>
<p><strong>Workshop Organized and/or Sponsored By:</strong> <em>National Science Foundation, Penn State (Earth and Environmental Systems Institute, Marcellus Center for Outreach and Research, Institutes for Energy and the Environment), University of Pittsburgh, Syracuse University, Evergreen Conservancy, Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection (PA DEP), Pennsylvania Department of Health</em></p>
<p><a href="2021-shale-network-workshop/2021_Abstracts.pdf">View the 2021 Shale Network Workshop Abstracts</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pdSK37cjHIY&amp;list=PLVEuDVfB7mM5iF6YgSQeWVyBQLIcUjk4D" target="_blank">Watch the pre-recorded talks</a></p>
<p><strong>Continuing professional education</strong></p>
<p>Attendees can receive:</p>
<ul>
<li>Professional Development Hours for professional engineers, land surveyors, and geologists.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Workshop</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2021-shale-network-workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2020 Shale Network Workshop [CANCELLED]</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2020-shale-network-workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>UPDATE: 2020 WORKSHOP CANCELLED DUE TO COVID-19 PANDEMIC</strong></p>
<p>To Shale Network participants:&nbsp;</p>
<p>The Shale Network Workshop team has decided that we need to cancel the Shale&nbsp;Network workshop for this spring because of the novel coronavirus. We make this decision based on the latest request from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention to cancel events scheduled within the next two months. We regret to cancel because this year’s lineup was to be terrific, covering many new and emerging topics including, ironically, aspects of issues around human health. We have chosen dates for next year, May 13-14, 2021, and we invite you to pencil this time in for the workshop, once again in State College, Pa.&nbsp;We worked very hard on the planning for this year and we very much hope that all of our speakers will commit to coming next year, perhaps for the same line-up for the agenda, but with, of course, updated talks. In addition, we hope to run the same (or better) field trip next year. In the meantime, please, please be healthy and safe. &nbsp;</p>
<p>Regards, The Shale Network Workshop Team<br>
Susan L. Brantley<br>
Distinguished Professor of Geosciences</p>
<p><strong>Workshop Announcement</strong></p>
<p>Registration for the ninth annual Shale Network Workshop is now open. The theme of the 2020 workshop is “Shale Gas: Future and Developing Issues” and includes presentations on the health effects related to shale gas development by Donna Vorhees, director of energy research at the Health Effects Institute, and Joan Casey, assistant professor of environmental health sciences at Columbia University. The workshop will be held May 14-15 at the Graduate Hotel in State College, Pa.</p>
<p>The workshop provides an opportunity for citizen scientists, researchers, government officials, energy company representatives, and environmental professionals to compare lessons learned about water and environmental issues within areas where shale energy development is occurring.</p>
<p>The 2020 workshop features a field trip to several alternative energy-related sites on the Penn State campus, including a gas-powered steam plant, solar array, nuclear reactor, and other available facilities. <strong>Participants who want to visit the nuclear reactor must provide their home address information when they register for the workshop.</strong> The tentative field trip schedule is as follows:</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
9:30 a.m.
</td>
<td>
Meet at The Graduate
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
9:45 a.m.
</td>
<td>
Depart for field trip
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
10:30 a.m.
</td>
<td>
Visit the Sandy Ridge wind farm (tentative per company approval)
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
11:15 a.m.
</td>
<td>
Depart from wind farm
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
12:00 p.m.
</td>
<td>
Arrive on Penn State campus, lunch (pack your own) with discussion on PSU campus energy conservation initiatives
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
1:00 p.m.
</td>
<td>
Break into two groups to tour the Brazealle Nuclear Reactor and East Campus Steam Plant
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
3:00 p.m.
</td>
<td>
Tour the Penn State solar array
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
4:00 p.m.
</td>
<td>
Arrive back at The Graduate
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Shale Network is a collaborative effort between Penn State, the University of Pittsburgh and the Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrologic Sciences Inc.&nbsp;(CUAHSI) to collect and analyze data on water quality in the Marcellus Shale drilling region. The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection participates in organizing parts of the workshop. Oak Ridge Associated Universities (ORAU) has also provided funding in past years.<br>
&nbsp; <strong>Agenda</strong></p>
<p><a href="2020-shale-network-workshop/Agenda.pdf">Click here for the 2020 Shale Network agenda</a></p>
<p><strong>Continuing professional education</strong></p>
<p>Attendees can receive:</p>
<ul>
<li>Professional Development Hours for professional engineers, land surveyors and geologists.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Workshop</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2020-shale-network-workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2020-shale-network-workshop/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2019 Shale Network Workshop</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2019-shale-network-workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Monitoring Communities and Their Environment</strong></p>
<p>The Shale Network will hold its eighth annual workshop at&nbsp;the Nittany Lion Inn in State College, Pa.&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Dates:</strong></p>
<p>May 16-17</p>
<p><strong>Location:</strong></p>
<p>The Nittany Lion Inn</p>
<p><strong>About the Workshop</strong></p>
<p>The workshop provides an opportunity for citizen scientists, researchers, government officials, energy company representatives, and environmental professionals to compare lessons learned about water and environmental issues within areas where shale energy development is occurring.</p>
<p>The 2019 workshop features a field trip to two shale energy-related sites that manage solid and liquid wastes derived from well drilling and oil and gas production. The first is a tour of the Eureka Resources Williamsport, Pa. facility, an oil and gas wastewater management plant. This facility is designed for the pretreatment, recycling and disposal of wastewater from natural gas drilling and production operations in the Marcellus and Utica Shales. The second is a tour of the Wayne Township Landfill in Clinton County, Pa. The landfill manages drilling cuttings and muds generated primarily from shale well drilling operations and uses some novel practices to minimize the industry’s environmental footprint. In addition, the facility hosts a compressed natural gas filling station for vehicles, including trash hauling vehicles. The tentative field trip schedule is as follows:</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<p>
9:30 a.m.
</p>
</td>
<td>
<p>
Meet in Nittany Lion Inn lobby
</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<p>
9:45 a.m.
</p>
</td>
<td>
<p>
Depart for Williamsport
</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<p>
11:00 a.m. - 12:00 p.m.
</p>
</td>
<td>
<p>
Tour Eureka Resources gas well wastewater treatment facility
</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<p>
12:00 p.m. - 1:00 p.m.
</p>
</td>
<td>
<p>
Bring your own lunch
</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<p>
1:00 p.m.
</p>
</td>
<td>
<p>
Depart for Wayne Township
</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<p>
1:30 - 3:30 p.m.
</p>
</td>
<td>
<p>
Tour Wayne Township Landfill
</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>
<p>
4:30 p.m.
</p>
</td>
<td>
<p>
Return to Nittany Lion Inn
</p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The Shale Network is a collaborative effort between Penn State, the University of Pittsburgh and the Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrologic Sciences Inc.&nbsp;(CUAHSI) to collect and analyze data on water quality in the Marcellus Shale drilling region. The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection participates in organizing parts of the workshop. Oak Ridge Associated Universities (ORAU) also provides funding.</p>
<p><strong>Agenda</strong></p>
<p><a href="2019-shale-network-workshop/Agenda.pdf">Click here for the 2019 Shale Network agenda</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Continuing Professional Education</strong></p>
<p>Attendees can receive:&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li>Professional Development Hours for professional engineers, land surveyors and geologists</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Workshop</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2019-shale-network-workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Trout Unlimited Releases Results Of Latest Watershed Snapshot Day</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Trout-Unlimited-Releases-Results-Of-Latest-Watershed-Snapshot-Day.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Trout-Unlimited-Releases-Results-Of-Latest-Watershed-Snapshot-Day/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>UNIVERSITY PARK, Pa. - Trout Unlimited has released the results of water samples taken during the latest Watershed Snapshot Day in Allegheny National Forest. Organized by Trout Unlimited, the U.S. Forest Service and Penn State, Watershed Snapshot Days&nbsp;bring&nbsp;researchers and citizen scientists together to sample dozens of streams throughout the forest for research and conservation purposes.</p>
<p>Watch the full video below.</p>
<iframe frameborder="0" height="315" scrolling="no" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wWw9spDaD14?start=3&quot;" width="560" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>K-12 Outreach</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Trout-Unlimited-Releases-Results-Of-Latest-Watershed-Snapshot-Day.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Trout-Unlimited-Releases-Results-Of-Latest-Watershed-Snapshot-Day/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bradford County Water Quality Improves; Impacts Rare Near Shale Gas Wells</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Bradford-County-Water-Quality-Improves-Impacts-Rare-Near-Shale-Gas-Wells.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Bradford-County-Water-Quality-Improves-Impacts-Rare-Near-Shale-Gas-Wells/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>UNIVERSITY PARK, Pa. — A new study of groundwater in a rural Pennsylvania county shows only rare instances of possible gas contamination amid an overall trend of improving water quality despite heavy Marcellus Shale development.</p>
<p>By investigating data from gas companies, the state, and the U.S. Geological Survey, researchers saw possible contamination by natural gas near no more than seven out of 1,385 shale wells studied in heavily drilled Bradford County. The rest of the water chemistry data highlighted that groundwater had either improved or remained level from samples taken prior to the 1990s.</p>
<p>“The most interesting thing we discovered was the groundwater chemistry in one of the areas most heavily developed for shale gas – an area with 1400 new gas wells – does not appear to be getting worse with time, and may even be getting better,” said Susan Brantley, director of Penn State’s Earth and Environmental Systems Institute and distinguished professor of geosciences. “But using data analytics we could also see rare sites that warrant more investigation for possible gas anomalies.”</p>
<p>Brantley and an interdisciplinary team of geoscientists and computer scientists used new data-mining techniques to study a large dataset of 11,000 groundwater samples from the 2010s, taken after drilling in Bradford County.</p>
<p>The team recently reported their findings in the journal Environmental Science &amp; Technology.</p>
<p>“Unlike previous studies, our findings show that groundwater quality might even be improving in an area heavily exploited for shale gas — northeastern Bradford,” said Tao Wen, a post-doctoral scholar in Penn State’s Earth and Environmental Systems Institute and lead author on the paper.</p>
<p>Find more details on the <a href="http://news.psu.edu/story/524986/2018/06/12/research/bradford-co-water-quality-improves-impacts-rare-near-shale-gas" target="_blank">PSU News</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <category>Research Updates</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Bradford-County-Water-Quality-Improves-Impacts-Rare-Near-Shale-Gas-Wells.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Bradford-County-Water-Quality-Improves-Impacts-Rare-Near-Shale-Gas-Wells/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2018 Shale Network Workshop</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2018-shale-network-workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Integrating data about shale gas development: Toward a more collaborative future</strong></p>
<p>The Shale Network held its seventh annual workshop May 17 and 18 at the Penn State University Park campus and in State College, Pa. The workshop was our largest yet, drawing a diverse group interested in water quality around the Marcellus Shale drilling region in Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>About 120 people attended all or parts of the workshop, which included a field trip and mock spill demonstration and computer module Thursday, May 17, and a poster session and presentations and discussions throughout the day Friday, May 18.</p>
<p>Citizen scientists, local high school students and teachers, academics, government employees, energy industry representatives and members of watershed groups all attended and interacted during the two-day event.</p>
<p>Of the 118 participants: 54 were from academia, including representatives from Penn State, Pitt, Syracuse, Cincinnati, Yale, Cornell, Colorado Boulder, Binghamton, Kutztown, Indiana University of Pennsylvania and the University of Rochester; 18 were from government agencies, including the U.S. Geological Survey, the Pa. Department of Conservation and Natural Resources, the Pa. Department of Environmental Protection, the Pa. Department of Health and the Ohio Department of Natural Resources; 14 from environmental/nonprofit grounds, including the Evergreen Conservancy, the Environmental Defense Fund, FracTracker Alliance, Trout Unlimited, the Health Effects Institute and the Pa Senior Environmental Corps; and 14 from industry/consulting groups, including Shell Oil, Chevron, Chesapeake Energy and Repsol Oil and Gas.</p>
<p>We appreciated everyone’s contributions, and are thankful for another great workshop.</p>
<p><strong>Presentations</strong></p>
<p><a href="2018-shale-network-workshop/4_Shale_network_2018.pdf">Characterization,potential toxicity, and fate of O&amp;G wastewaters spread on roads in Pennsylvania</a> (Travis Tasker)</p>
<p><a href="2018-shale-network-workshop/Lackey_2018_SGN.pdf">Mining Oil and Gas Well Integrity Data in Colorado and New Mexico</a> (Greg Lackey)</p>
<p><a href="2018-shale-network-workshop/Fowler_Regulating_Beneficial_Reuse.pdf">The World of “Beneficial Reuse”: Regulating the Spread of Oil and Gas Wastewater on Roads</a> (Lara Fowler)</p>
<p><a href="2018-shale-network-workshop/Shale_Network_Presentation_EnvJustice_2018.pdf">Sociodemographic Predictors of Hydraulic Fracturing Wastewater&nbsp;Well Siting in Ohio</a>&nbsp;(Genevieve Silva, Joshua Warren, Nicole C. Deziel)</p>
<p><strong>Date(s):</strong>&nbsp;May 17&nbsp;and 18, 2018</p>
<p><strong>Location:</strong>&nbsp;Atherton Hotel,&nbsp;State College, Pa., and Penn State, University Park campus</p>
<p><strong>About the Workshop</strong></p>
<p>The workshop provides&nbsp;an opportunity for nonscientists, researchers, experts, government officials, and members of the gas and environmental industries to compare lessons learned about water issues within the northeastern region of shale gas development.&nbsp;Participants take part in&nbsp;sharing and interpreting water&nbsp;data related to shale gas development.</p>
<p>The Shale Network is a collaborative effort between Penn State, the University of Pittsburgh and the Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrologic Sciences Inc.&nbsp;(CUAHSI) to collect and analyze data on water quality in the Marcellus Shale drilling region.&nbsp;The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection&nbsp;participates in organizing parts of the&nbsp;workshop.&nbsp;Oak Ridge Associated Universities (ORAU) also provides&nbsp;funding.</p>
<p>The workshop steering committee for 2018 includes Susan Brantley, Dave Yoxtheimer and Matt Carroll (Penn State), Radisav Vidic (Pitt), Bob Hendricks (Shell), Liza Brazil (CUASHI), and Cindy Rogers (Evergreen Conservancy).&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Agenda</strong></p>
<p><a href="2018-shale-network-workshop/2018_Shale_Network_Workshop_Agenda.pdf">Click here for the 2018 Shale Network agenda</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>2018 Workshop Registration</strong></p>
<p>Registration is closed&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Continuing Professional Education</strong></p>
<p>Attendees can receive:&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li>Professional Development Hours for professional engineers, land surveyors and geologists</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Workshop</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2018-shale-network-workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Students See Green Mock Spill Illustrates Potential Impact Of Wastewater Leak</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Students-See-Green-Mock-Spill-Illustrates-Potential-Impact-Of-Wastewater-Leak.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Students-See-Green-Mock-Spill-Illustrates-Potential-Impact-Of-Wastewater-Leak/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>SNOW SHOE TOWNSHIP, Pa. — Bright green water swirled around Mariah Airey’s boots as it made its way into Black Moshannon Creek.</p>
<p>A freshman at State College Area High School, Airey watched as green dye trickled down a tributary, mixed with the clear water in the creek and then rushed downstream.</p>
<p>A group of State High students participated in a mock spill event last week simulating what might happen if a contaminate spill reached the stream.&nbsp;</p>
<p>“When it reached Black Mo, it surprised me how far it went,” Airey said. “I thought my eyes were deceiving me.”</p>
<p>Airey and her classmates are part of TeenShale Network, a group of high school students working with Penn State scientists to monitor water quality in local streams around Marcellus Shale development.</p>
<p>Penn State researchers and Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection staff placed environmentally safe dye in the creek to help the students visualize what might happen if a truck hauling wastewater from a Marcellus Shale well site crashed and spilled its contents.</p>
<p>“There are a series of wells up on the hill, and trucks carry brine from the production of shale gas out of this watershed to treatment facilities,” said David Yoxtheimer, a research assistant in Penn State’s Earth and Environmental Systems Institute. “We set the stage that a brine truck rolled over and spilled some of its brine into the creek.”</p>
<p>Read more about the project on the <a href="http://news.psu.edu/story/517637/2018/04/23/impact/students-see-green-mock-spill-illustrates-potential-impact-wastewater" target="_blank">PSU News</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>K-12 Outreach</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Students-See-Green-Mock-Spill-Illustrates-Potential-Impact-Of-Wastewater-Leak.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Students-See-Green-Mock-Spill-Illustrates-Potential-Impact-Of-Wastewater-Leak/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Driven Dialogue Scientists Bring Groups Together On Water Quality Concerns</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Data-Driven-Dialogue-Scientists-Bring-Groups-Together-On-Water-Quality-Concerns.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Data-Driven-Dialogue-Scientists-Bring-Groups-Together-On-Water-Quality-Concerns/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>UNIVERSITY PARK, Pa. — It’s been a decade since the start of the Marcellus Shale gas boom in Pennsylvania, and today more than 10,000 unconventional gas wells dot the state’s hills and valleys.</p>
<p>The industry’s rapid development created economic opportunities for many, but also brought environmental concerns, and sometimes led to contentious conversations.</p>
<p>A team of researchers studying water quality around hydraulic fracturing, the process used to extract gas from rock deep underground, have found a blueprint to move those conversations forward.</p>
<p>Shale Network has for the past six years fostered a dialogue about shale drilling between concerned citizens, watershed groups, government regulators and personnel from large energy companies by focusing on publicly available water quality data.</p>
<p>An annual workshop hosted at the University Park campus gives people a chance to come together, learn about the latest water quality research and data, and talk about ways to move forward together.</p>
<p>“I don’t believe that anyone else was able to bring such a diverse group of people together to discuss this extremely complex problem from their unique perspectives but with a common goal to jointly advance the understanding of this problem and rationally discuss possible ways forward,” said Radisav Vidic, a professor of environmental engineering at the University of Pittsburgh and Shale Network member.</p>
<p>A shared interest in gathering, discussing and improving water quality data among diverse groups can lead to productive conversations that data alone cannot address, the scientists reported in an article published in the journal Science.</p>
<p>“We’ve been trying to figure out how to pull people together and look at numbers to understand impacts,” said Susan Brantley, distinguished professor of geosciences and director of the Earth and Environmental Systems Institute at Penn State. “That can lead to better decisions.</p>
<p>“That’s really what Shale Network is all about,” said Brantley, who is lead investigator of the group. “We want to help everyone understand what the numbers — in this case water chemistry numbers — mean related to shale gas development.”</p>
<p>For the past six years, Shale Network researchers have collected and published water quality data online. Their database contains more than a million pieces of data from 28,000 locations across the state, some never available before. The Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrologic Science (CUAHSI) hosts the public database with funding from the National Science Foundation (NSF).</p>
<p>“We have all these data points that are starting to be at our fingertips, and we have computational tools to work with the data,” Brantley said. “Yet, the numbers don’t mean anything unless you are working together. Not just with geologists or geochemists, but people who live in the area the data comes from. You need that collaboration to understand what the numbers mean. Local community members teach us about their landscapes and their needs.”</p>
<p>Brantley said people know what is happening in their backyards. Watershed groups near Pittsburgh, for instance, know to look out for discharge from old coal mines, which wouldn’t be a factor in other parts of the state.</p>
<p>The database has proven useful, but even more important has been the process of building it, the researchers said in the paper. Collaborations between diverse stakeholders have helped forge a social network with diverse perspectives and concerns.</p>
<p>“We may have developed a blueprint for how to engage different stakeholders and develop a commonality of purpose even in something as controversial and complicated as unconventional gas extraction,” Vidic said. “Perhaps this blueprint can be applied for the same problem elsewhere in the world or for other complex problems.”</p>
<p>Shale Network researchers act as honest brokers in discussions like those that take place at the group’s annual workshops.</p>
<p>“We are not trying to prove fracking is bad,” Brantley said. “We are not trying to prove water quality is perfect. We are trying to look at what the water chemistry looks like in the areas where fracking is occurring and help all kinds of people talk about that together.”</p>
<p>Co-authors include Kathryn Brasier, associate professor of rural sociology, Dave Yoxtheimer, EESI research assistant, and Tao Wen, a post-doctoral scholar, all at Penn State; and Candie Wilderman, professor at Dickinson College.</p>
<p>Founded in 2010 with NSF funding, the Shale Network is a collaborative effort between Penn State, the University of Pittsburgh, Dickinson College and CUAHSI to collect and analyze data on water quality in the Marcellus Shale drilling region.</p>
<p>Please read details on the <a href="http://news.psu.edu/story/503237/2018/01/31/impact/data-driven-dialogue-scientists-bring-groups-together-water-quality" target="_blank">PSU News</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Data-Driven-Dialogue-Scientists-Bring-Groups-Together-On-Water-Quality-Concerns.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Data-Driven-Dialogue-Scientists-Bring-Groups-Together-On-Water-Quality-Concerns/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Snapshot Day Brings Pennsylvania Water Quality Into Focus</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Snapshot-Day-Brings-Pennsylvania-Water-Quality-Into-Focus.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Snapshot-Day-Brings-Pennsylvania-Water-Quality-Into-Focus/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>SHEFFIELD, Pa. — Bill Eckert slipped into his hip waders and splashed through the small stream near his cabin in the Allegheny National Forest.</p>
<p>He didn’t bring his fishing pole this time. Instead, Eckert bent down and let the cold water fill the assorted bottles he carried.</p>
<p>Eckert was among a few dozen volunteers collecting water samples that could help researchers develop a clearer picture of water quality in Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>“If you enjoy the outdoors, you’re sort of concerned about preserving it, making sure the streams are clean,” Eckert said on a cool October morning.</p>
<p>The effort was part of Snapshot Day, a recurring event organized by Penn State researchers and Trout Unlimited to get volunteers out to sample streams in different parts of the state.</p>
<p>Back at Penn State, researchers test the water samples for things like methane concentration, which can be an indicator of contamination from Marcellus Shale gas extraction or old, forgotten conventional oil and gas wells.</p>
<p>“We started this project initially to monitor streams around Pennsylvania using volunteers to help look at methane in stream water,” said Joshua Woda, a graduate student in the Department of Geosciences who is involved in the project.</p>
<p>The tests can help fingerprint the methane’s source, weeding out natural causes often found in streams from things like swamps or bogs.</p>
<p>If scientists find elevated methane levels, they can identify the area as a hot spot and put more resources into investigating what is happening there.</p>
<p>“We look for these elevated values, and when we see them over a certain threshold, we start to ask questions,” Woda said. “Why is this elevated?”</p>
<p>The work is part of a larger effort to help better our understanding of baseline water quality across the state. The data could be an important measuring stick if we someday face future water quality issues.</p>
<p>But gathering the information is no small task. There are hundreds of streams in Pennsylvania and only so many researchers working on the project. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>
<p>“By volunteering to collect water samples around their communities, citizen scientists can play an important role in helping researchers better understand water quality in Pennsylvania,”&nbsp;said Susan Brantley, professor of geosciences and director of the Earth and Environmental Systems Institute at Penn State, and Woda’s adviser. “These samples help paint a clearer picture of baseline water quality around our communities, and can be used to watch for potential future environmental impacts.”</p>
<p>In the Allegheny National Forest, researchers were interested in the possible impacts of so-called orphaned and abandoned oil or gas wells. Some of these wells date back more than a hundred years, and if they aren’t properly plugged, or if they have been damaged over time, they could potentially allow contaminants to enter the atmosphere or waterways. Estimates put the number of unlocated wells as high as 500,000.</p>
<p>On Snapshot Day, volunteers fanned out across the forest in groups, visiting small headwater streams, so numerous that they sometimes receive less monitoring than the larger streams and rivers they feed.</p>
<p>“There are just so many of them that agencies don’t have the capacity to comprehensively monitor them,” said Jacob Lemon, a science coordinator with Trout Unlimited. “That’s why it’s really important to get volunteers in there. You can get local boots on the ground. These people are the ones that spend time out there. They know what the streams are like and what they should be like.”</p>
<p>The event is a way to get more Trout Unlimited members involved with ongoing water quality monitoring projects the group regularly undertakes.&nbsp;</p>
<p>For Eckert, who was attending his first Snapshot Day, any time spent among the trees and streams in the forest is good. Helping monitor water quality is an added bonus. “We’re not wasting time,” he said.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>K-12 Outreach</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Snapshot-Day-Brings-Pennsylvania-Water-Quality-Into-Focus.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Snapshot-Day-Brings-Pennsylvania-Water-Quality-Into-Focus/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>TeenShale Network Gears Up For Another Year</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/TeenShale-Network-Gears-Up-For-Another-Year.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/TeenShale-Network-Gears-Up-For-Another-Year/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Local high school students stepped back into their hip waders and ventured into the cool, rushing water of Black Moshannon Creek this week.</p>
<p>The students are part of TeenShale Network, an ongoing water quality monitoring run by Penn State’s Earth and Environmental Systems Institute.</p>
<p>TeenShale gives State College Area School District students a chance to learn real science alongside professionals. Their work collecting samples also leads to better baseline data about the state’s waterways.</p>
<p>The students are looking for changes in water quality that could be caused by pollutants from sources like nearby natural gas drilling sites.</p>
<p>Hydraulic fracturing, or fracking, is used to extract natural gas from rocks deep underground and the process has been controversial due to potential environmental impacts.</p>
<p>This year, the students will also be exploring the impact of Orphaned and Abandoned oil and gas wells. It is estimated there are many thousands of these wells scattered across the state, many lost to time. And if they are improperly plugged or damaged, they can release pollutants into water and the atmosphere.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>K-12 Outreach</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/TeenShale-Network-Gears-Up-For-Another-Year.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/TeenShale-Network-Gears-Up-For-Another-Year/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Shale Network Workshop Brings Diverse Group Together For Water Quality Discussions</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Shale-Network-Workshop-Brings-Diverse-Group-Together-For-Water-Quality-Discussions.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Shale-Network-Workshop-Brings-Diverse-Group-Together-For-Water-Quality-Discussions/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>STATE COLLEGE, Pa. — The Shale Network held its sixth annual workshop May 18 and 19 at the Penn State University Park Campus, and in State College, Pa. The workshop again drew a large, diverse group of participants interested in water quality around the Marcellus Shale drilling region in Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>Representatives from academia, government agencies, energy industries, environmental groups joined citizen scientists and high school students and teachers during the two-day event.</p>
<p>About 100 people attended all or parts of the workshop, which included a field trip, computer module and poster session on Thursday, May 18, and a daylong session of presentations and discussion on Friday, May 19.</p>
<p>Of the 100 participants: 35 were from academia, including representatives from Penn State, Pittsburgh, Cornell, Syracuse, Indiana University of Pennsylvania, Colorado School of Mines and Lock Haven; 25 were from government agencies, including the U.S. Geological Survey, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, the Pa. Department of Environmental Protection and the Pa. Department of Conservation and Natural Resources; 35 were from environmental/non-profit groups, including Trout Unlimited, FracTracker Alliance, Environmental Defense Fund and Pa. Senior Environmental Corps.; and nine were from energy companies like Chesapeake Energy, XTO Energy and Pennsylvania General Energy.</p>
<p>We appreciated everyone’s contributions, and are thankful for another great workshop.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Shale-Network-Workshop-Brings-Diverse-Group-Together-For-Water-Quality-Discussions.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Shale-Network-Workshop-Brings-Diverse-Group-Together-For-Water-Quality-Discussions/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2017 Shale Network Workshop</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2017-shale-network-workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Sharing data about shale gas development: from drilling to disposal</strong></p>
<p>The Shale Network held its sixth annual workshop May 18 and 19 at the Penn State University Park Campus, and in State College, Pa. The workshop again drew a large, diverse group of participants interested in water quality around the Marcellus Shale drilling region in Pennsylvania.</p>
<p>Representatives from academia, government agencies, energy industries, environmental groups joined citizen scientists and high school students and teachers during the two-day event.</p>
<p>About 100 people attended all or parts of the workshop, which included a field trip, computer module and poster session on Thursday, May 18, and a daylong session of presentations and discussion on Friday, May 19.</p>
<p>Of the 100 participants: 35 were from academia, including representatives from Penn State, Pittsburgh, Cornell, Syracuse, Indiana University of Pennsylvania, Colorado School of Mines and Lock Haven; 25 were from government agencies, including the U.S. Geological Survey, the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, the Pa. Department of Environmental Protection and the Pa. Department of Conservation and Natural Resources; 35 were from environmental/non-profit groups, including Trout Unlimited, FracTracker Alliance, Environmental Defense Fund and Pa. Senior Environmental Corps.; and nine were from energy companies like Chesapeake Energy, XTO Energy and Pennsylvania General Energy.</p>
<p>We appreciated everyone’s contributions, and are thankful for another great workshop.</p>
<p><strong>Date(s):</strong></p>
<p>May 18 and 19, 2017</p>
<p><strong>Location:</strong></p>
<p>Atherton Hotel,&nbsp;State College, Pa., and Penn State, University Park campus</p>
<p><strong>About the Workshop</strong></p>
<p>All participants took part in&nbsp;sharing and interpreting water quality and quantity data related to shale gas development.</p>
<p>The Shale Network is a collaborative effort between Penn State, the University of Pittsburgh, and the Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrologic Sciences Inc.&nbsp;(CUAHSI) to collect and analyze data on water quality in the Marcellus Shale drilling region. The workshop provided an opportunity for nonscientists, researchers, experts, government officials, and members of the gas and environmental industries to compare lessons learned about water issues within the northeastern region of shale gas development. The Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection is co-organized&nbsp;the workshop. Oak Ridge Associated Universities (ORAU) also provided funding.</p>
<p><strong>Agenda</strong></p>
<p><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Final_Agenda.pdf">Click here for the 2017 Shale Network agenda</a>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Presentations</strong>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Woda_Shale_Network_Talk_2017.pdf">Engaging Angler Scientists in Methane Research: A Collaborative Approach</a> (Josh Woda, Jacob Lemon, Frederick B. Zelt, Susan Brantley)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Vidic_2017_ShaleNetwork.pdf">Changes in the Quantity and Quality of Produced Water from Appalachian Shale Energy Development and their Implications for Water Reuse</a> (Radisav D. Vidic, Dave Yoxtheimer)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Wise_MIA_05182017.pdf">DEP’s&nbsp;Mechanical Integrity Assessment Program</a> (Harry Wise)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Tyrell_PSU_Talk.pdf">Proactively&nbsp;Addressing&nbsp;Induced Seismicity</a> (Tim Tyrrell)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Steffy_2017_Shale_Meeting.pdf">Preliminary Results from Stream Methane Monitoring in the Marcellus Shale Region of the Susquehanna River Basin</a> (Luanne Steffy)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Skoff_UIC_Well_Pres_051917.pdf">How many disposal wells does PA need and where can they be located?</a> (Dale E. Skoff)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Rice_ShaleNetwork.pdf">Methane leakage rom hydrocarbon wellbores into overlying groundwater: Numerical investigation of the multiphase flow processes governing migration</a> (Amy Rice, John McCray, Kamini&nbsp;Singha)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Rudolchick_ShaleNetwork2017.pdf">Quantifying Methane Emissions from Abandoned Legacy Gas Wells in Indiana County, Pennsylvania</a> (Molly Rudolchick, Steve Hovan)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Pelepko_Waste_Management_Trends_05172017.pdf">Production Waste Trends and Management</a> (Seth Pelepko)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Nyblade_ShaleNetwork_5_19_17.pdf">Seismicity in Pennsylvania and the Pennsylvania State Seismic Network</a> (Andy Nyblade)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Hughes_Plenary.pdf">Black Shale Waste Disposal Concerns</a> (Bill Hughes)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Myers_Well_Construction_and_Cementing.pdf">Well Construction and Cementing Practices in Shale and Salt Water Disposal Wells</a> (Roger Myers)&nbsp;</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Khalequzzman_2017_ShaleNetwork.pdf">Characterizing Sources of Stream Turbidity in the Marcellus Shale Gas-Well Drilling Region in Central Pennsylvania</a> (Matt Bell, Rose Nash, Md. Khalequzzaman)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/BrantleyWorkshop_2017_Intro_and_ClosingRemarks.pdf">6th Annual Shale Network Workshop opening and closing remarks</a> (Susan Brantley)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Hintz_Shale_Workshop_5-19-17_SRBC.pdf">Continuous Water Quality Trends Adjusted for Seasonality and Streamflow&nbsp;in the Susquehanna River Basin</a> (Dawn Hintz, Graham Markowitz)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Baka_2017_Shale_Network.pdf">E-Governance as a data source for evaluating stakeholder positions on hydraulic fracturing regulation</a> (Jennifer Baka)</li>
<li><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Allard_ShaleNetwork.pdf">PA TENORM Study &amp; Regulatory Framework</a> (David J. Allard)&nbsp;</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Continuing Professional Education</strong></p>
<p><a href="2017-shale-network-workshop/Continuing-Professional-Education-Credits.docx">Click here for information on earning continuing education credits and PDHs</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Workshop</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2017-shale-network-workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Big Data Approach To Water Quality Applied At Shale Drilling Sites</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Big-Data-Approach-To-Water-Quality-Applied-At-Shale-Drilling-Sites.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>UNIVERSITY PARK, Pa. — A computer program is diving deep into water quality data from Pennsylvania, helping scientists detect potential environmental impacts of Marcellus Shale gas drilling.</p>
<p>The work, supported by a new $1 million grant from the National Science Foundation, pairs a cross-disciplinary team of Penn State computer scientists and geoscientists studying methane concentrations in the state’s streams, rivers and private water wells.</p>
<p>“We want to take a data-driven approach to assess the impact of shale gas development,” said&nbsp;Zhenhui “Jessie” Li, assistant professor of&nbsp;information sciences and technology, Penn State, and co-principal investigator on the project. “We are using data-mining techniques and learning computer models to look at how methane concentration correlates with other factors, like distance from unconventional shale gas wells and geological features such as faults.”</p>
<p>Methane occurs naturally in waterways, but may also be released by unconventional drilling, or fracking, associated with natural gas development. While environmental impacts from shale drilling appear to be rare compared to the number of drilled wells, the testing will give scientists a better idea of how and why they do occur.</p>
<p>Penn State geoscientists have studied methane concentrations around shale gas drilling for years and have collected large datasets from samples taken by researchers, environmental groups and government agencies. However, sifting through big data is labor intensive, and complex patterns that might reveal potential problems can be difficult for humans to spot.</p>
<p>“It’s always been frustrating to me because we get these water datasets that are sort of here, there and everywhere, and you can’t put them together into a scientific explanation,” said&nbsp;Susan Brantley, distinguished professor of&nbsp;geosciences&nbsp;and director of the&nbsp;Earth and Environmental Systems Institute, Penn State, and principal investigator on the project. “It’s like a jigsaw puzzle with a lot of pieces missing. The story is still there, but you can’t see it as a human being. I think it’s possible the computer techniques that Jessie has can help us pull that story out and fill in some of the missing pieces.”</p>
<p>For more information on this project, visit <a href="http://news.psu.edu/story/440879/2016/12/07/research/big-data-approach-water-quality-applied-shale-drilling-sites" target="_blank">PSU News</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>Publication</category>
  <category>Research Updates</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Big-Data-Approach-To-Water-Quality-Applied-At-Shale-Drilling-Sites.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Conference Takes Aim At State’s Orphan Well Problem</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Conference-Takes-Aim-At-States-Orphan-Well-Problem.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Conference-Takes-Aim-At-States-Orphan-Well-Problem/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>More than 150 years after the first commercial oil well was drilled in Pennsylvania, decades of energy exploration have resulted in hundreds of thousands of abandoned, lost and forgotten oil and gas wells scattered across the state.</p>
<p>Researchers at Penn State are among a number of organizations in Pennsylvania working to locate and assess these so called orphaned and abandoned wells, which if not properly plugged, or if damaged over time, can potentially cause air and water pollution.</p>
<p>Members of these organizations met together for the first time in September on Penn State’s University Park campus for the Orphaned Wells Conference — a chance to discuss their work and talk about what they can accomplish by collaborating.</p>
<p>“I think having everyone at the same table really opened collaborative doors,” said Nooreen Meghani, a research assistant in Penn State’s Earth and Environmental Systems Institute. “It inspired a lot of conversation about how we can help each other.”</p>
<p>The conference, hosted by Penn State’s Marcellus Matters program, drew representatives from Indiana University of Pennsylvania, Mansfield University of Pennsylvania, the state Department of Environmental Protection, Save our Streams Pa., and the Clearfield County Senior Environmental Corps.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Conference-Takes-Aim-At-States-Orphan-Well-Problem.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Conference-Takes-Aim-At-States-Orphan-Well-Problem/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>State College High School Students Testing The Waters At Black Mo</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/State-College-High-School-Students-Testing-The-Waters-At-Black-Mo.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/State-College-High-School-Students-Testing-The-Waters-At-Black-Mo/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>If anything happens to the water in Black Moshannon Creek, a group of State College Area School District earth science students might just be the first to know.</p>
<p>The teens, mostly from State High but with a few advanced eighth-graders thrown in, have been monitoring the watershed this year in partnership with researchers from Penn State’s Earth and Environmental Systems Institute.</p>
<p>The project, called TeenShale Network, gives students a chance to learn science exists outside of their textbooks and classrooms, and that their work can make a difference in the real world.</p>
<p>“I think TSN is important, because I think that people should have more awareness for the environment when they are younger,” said Toby Ma, an eighth-grader participating in the group.</p>
<p>Students, their teachers and Penn State researchers traveled to Black Moshannon State Park several times in the fall and spring to sample stream water.</p>
<p>They are looking for changes in water quality that could be caused by pollutants from sources like nearby natural gas drilling sites.</p>
<p>Hydraulic fracturing, or fracking, is used to extract natural gas from rocks deep underground and the process has been controversial due to potential environmental impacts.</p>
<p>Sampling the stream gives students a baseline of water quality, and going back lets them see if anything has changed due to fracking or other factors.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Check out the full story at&nbsp;<a href="http://www.centredaily.com/news/local/education/penn-state/article78736852.html" target="_blank">www.centredaily.com/news/local/education/penn-state/article78736852.html</a></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>K-12 Outreach</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/State-College-High-School-Students-Testing-The-Waters-At-Black-Mo.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/State-College-High-School-Students-Testing-The-Waters-At-Black-Mo/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2016 Shale Network Workshop</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2016-shale-network-workshop.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><strong>Science and cooperation around water quality data and legacy wells in shale gas basins</strong></p>
<p>The fifth annual Shale Network workshop took place May 19 and 20, drawing a large, diverse group including government workers, industry representatives, environmental group members, students and academics. About 97 people attended all or parts of the workshop, including a field trip, poster session,&nbsp;computer module and daylong session of presentations and discussions.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Of the 97 participants:&nbsp;36 were from academia, including representatives from Princeton University, Penn State University, the University of Pittsburgh, the Colorado School of Mines,&nbsp;Binghamton University and Duquesne University; 18 were from government agencies, including the US Geological Survey, the US Department of Energy, the US Fish and Wildlife Service,&nbsp;the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection, and the Maryland Department of the Environment;&nbsp;11 were from environmental groups/non-profit groups, including Trout Unlimited, Friends for Environmental Justice and the Centre County Pennsylvania Senior Environmental Corps; seven were consultants or representing industry,&nbsp;including Shell, Chesapeake Energy, and Leidos; 17 were State College high school students and eight were members of the Shale Network committee.</p>
<p>We appreciated everyone’s contributions, and are thankful for another great workshop.</p>
<p><strong>Date(s):</strong></p>
<p>May 19 and 20, 2016</p>
<p><strong>Location:</strong></p>
<p>Atherton Hotel,&nbsp;State College, PA.&nbsp;(Adjacent to the Penn State University Park campus.)</p>
<p><strong>About the Workshop</strong></p>
<p>All participants took part in&nbsp;sharing and interpreting water quality and quantity data related to shale gas development.</p>
<p>The Shale Network is a collaborative effort between Penn State, Pitt, Dickinson and the Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrologic Sciences Inc.&nbsp;(CUAHSI) to collect and analyze data on water quality in the Marcellus Shale drilling region. The workshop provided an opportunity for nonscientists, researchers, experts, government officials, and members of the gas and environmental industries to compare lessons learned about water issues within the northeastern region of shale gas development.</p>
<p><strong>Agenda</strong></p>
<p>The <a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/Final_Agenda_Shale_Network_2016.pdf">2016 Workshop Agenda</a> is available</p>
<p>A complete <a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/Shale-Network-Workshop-Field-Trip-Itinerary.docx">field trip itinerary</a> is also available&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Presentations</strong></p>
<p>The presentation slides are now available:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/1.pdf">Science and Cooperation around Water Quality Data and Legacy Wells</a> (Brantley et al)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/2.pdf">Analysis of Methane Concentrations in Pennsylvania Stream and Groundwater in Collavoration with Citizen Scientists</a> (Jake Lemon, Anna Wendt, Susan Brantley)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/3.pdf">Evaluation of a Rapid Airborne Method for Locating Legacy Wells in Pennsylvania</a> (Richard Hammack, James Sams, Garret Veloski, and Rod Diehl)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/4.pdf">Detecting surface water contamination from drilling operations in Pennsylvania using publicly available water quality databases</a> (Anna Wendt et al)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/5.pdf">Assessing Well Water Quality in Southwestern Pennsylvania</a> (John F. Stolz)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/6.pdf">Orphan and Abandoned Oil and Gas Wells in Pa</a> (Nooreen Meghani)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/7.pdf">What to do with Produced Water when its Reuse for Hyraulic Fracturing is No Longer Feasible?</a> (Omkar Lokare, Sakineh Tavakkoli, Vikas Khanna, Radisav Vidic)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/8.pdf">NURE Legacy Groundwater Data: Evaluation of Basin-Scale Factors Influencing Shallow Brine and Halite Groundwater Impacts</a> (Garth Llewellyn)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/9.pdf">Investigations of the Depth of Freshwater in Fractured-Bedrock Aquifers Penetrated by Deep Boreholes in Northern Pa</a> (Dennis Risser, John Williams)</li>
<li><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/10.pdf">Application of AMD for Produced Water Reuse can Facilitate Byproduct Recovery and Permanent NORM Sequestration</a> (Tieyuan Zhang, Can He, Radisav Vidic)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Methane Module</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://serc.carleton.edu/hydromodules/units/143615.html" target="_blank">Click here</a> to complete exercises that&nbsp;guide you through the initial stages of a hypothetical water supply complaint investigation where methane has been detected in surface water in Pa.&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>2016 Workshop Registration</strong></p>
<p>Registration is closed&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Continuing Professional Education</strong></p>
<p><a href="2016-shale-network-workshop/Continuing-Professional-Education-Credits.docx">Click here for information on earning continuing education credits</a>&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Workshop</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2016-shale-network-workshop.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/2016-shale-network-workshop/image.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>TeenShale Network Returns To The Field For Another Year</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/TeenShale-Network-Returns-To-The-Field-For-Another-Year.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/TeenShale-Network-Returns-To-The-Field-For-Another-Year/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>A group of local high school students are&nbsp;slipping into their hipwaders and wading&nbsp;back into the TeenShale Network.&nbsp;</p>
<p>With the school year back in full swing, students at State College High School have resumed work on the project, which pairs the youngsters with Penn State researchers to monitor water quality in Black Moshannon Creek.</p>
<p>This year, 28 students are taking part in TeenShale network, ranging from 8th to 11th grade. They will build on work the returning students have done the past three years, and search for their own hypotheses in their data.&nbsp;</p>
<p>They learn about geology and geochemistry and about how potential environmental impacts like hydraulic fracturing could affect waterways.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The students will collect water samples during bi-weekly field trips at Black Moshannon State Park&nbsp;starting in mid-Octorber, and will work to analyize those samples in the classroom.</p>
<p>The project will culminate this year in April with a visit of the University of PIttsburgh Mobile Science Labortary.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>K-12 Outreach</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/TeenShale-Network-Returns-To-The-Field-For-Another-Year.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/TeenShale-Network-Returns-To-The-Field-For-Another-Year/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Shale Network Fosters Collaboration, Focuses on Water Quality</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Shale-Network-Fosters-collaboration-focuses-on-water-quality.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Shale-Network-Fosters-collaboration-focuses-on-water-quality/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>STATE COLLEGE, Pa. — A diverse group — from natural gas industry representatives to environmental advocates — gathered recently to discuss the impact of gas drilling on waterways at the 2015 Shale Network Workshop.</p>
<p>The annual workshop gives scientists a chance to share what they’ve learned over the last year about the impact of Marcellus shale gas drilling on the region’s streams and rivers, and to plan the best way to monitor water quality going forward.</p>
<p>The workshop also brings together groups that might not otherwise sit down to share concerns, observations and data – including citizen scientists, faculty, researchers and representatives from industry, government agencies and nonprofits.</p>
<p>“It is important to have these groups together because it is so rare for industry personnel, watershed groups, government agency workers and academics to interact informally and while discussing science – in a non-combative atmosphere,” said Susan Brantley, distinguished professor of geosciences and director of the Earth and Environmental Systems Institute (EESI) at Penn State.</p>
<p>“By promoting excellent science in a venue where researchers talk to non-researchers, an atmosphere is created that allows real conversation,” Brantley said. “One of the reasons that Shale Network can do this is that it has been funded by the National Science Foundation and by Penn State, both of which are honest brokers in the shale gas debates.”</p>
<p>The NSF-funded Shale Network is a collaborative effort to collect and analyze data on water quality in the Marcellus shale region. Its members include faculty and researchers from Penn State, the University of Pittsburgh, Dickinson College and the Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrologic Science Inc.&nbsp;(CUAHSI).</p>
<p>In its fourth year, the conference drew about 80 participants, including representatives from Chesapeake Energy, the Susquehanna River Basin Commission, the Washington County Watershed Alliance, the US Geological Survey, the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection and NSF.</p>
<p>Shale Network hosted the event through EESI at the Atherton Hotel in State College. Participants focused on what they have learned so far about the impact of natural gas drilling on water quality and where future efforts should be directed.</p>
<p>“This year we further discussed both the fact the only a very few significant problems have been identified in water quality data in Pennsylvania that can be attributed to shale gas activities, but that some of these problems must nonetheless be better understood,” Brantley said. “One area of growing interest is the idea that we might want to monitor methane dissolved in streams as a way to look for leakage of gas into aquifers.”</p>
<p>At the conference, Brantley discussed enlisting citizen scientists to help gather baseline information on area waterways using a new stream-based monitoring technique that can detect methane levels. Baseline information helps researchers detect future changes in water quality.</p>
<p>The data is important as some have raised concerns that hydraulic fracturing or fracking, the process used to extract gas or oil from shale deep beneath the ground, could lead to potential pollution of waterways because of spills or improperly sealed sites.</p>
<p>Shale Network has already collected a large database from water samples from the region. Software designed by CUAHSI and made publically available lets researchers track data to detect possible changes in water quality.</p>
<p>Funded by a four-year grant from the NSF, the Shale Network is in its final year. Researchers are looking at options for continuing the project. Data will continue to be available through CUASHI.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Shale-Network-Fosters-collaboration-focuses-on-water-quality.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/Shale-Network-Fosters-collaboration-focuses-on-water-quality/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>State High Students Partner With Penn State To Monitor Water Quality</title>
  <link>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/State-High-Students-Partner-With-Penn-State-To-Monitor-Water-Quality.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/State-High-Students-Partner-With-Penn-State-To-Monitor-Water-Quality/image.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>RUSH TOWNSHIP, Pa. – The boots Maria Rodriguez-Hertz wore kept out the water but not the numbing cold from Black Moshannon Creek.</p>
<p>Rodriguez-Hertz, a State College high school sophomore, waded into the stream along with her classmates to collect water samples and record data for the TeenShale Network.</p>
<p>The network is a collaboration between Penn State researchers and high school science students and teachers. Together, they monitor the stream for potential environmental impacts, such as from Marcellus Shale gas drilling.</p>
<p>With the help of the students, the network is growing.</p>
<p>Last year, students collected data from only one site. This year, two new sites were added downstream, strategically chosen because they are close to Marcellus Shale well pads.</p>
<p>“Having multiple locations lets students see how the water changes as it flows downstream and is exposed to both natural and man-made influences,” said Penn State researcher Jennifer Williams. “I think it’s incredibly valuable for the students to see how one site at a local state park that is considered pristine and utilized in a variety of different ways can change over its course of reach downstream as it passed through our community.”</p>
<p>Nearby Marcellus Shale wells are one possible man-made influence. To get the gas out of the ground, a process is used called hydraulic fracturing, or fracking. This process is controversial and scientists have been studying its possible environmental impact.</p>
<p>The students are providing scientists with baseline data on what the stream looks like now, which can be used as a reference to examine possible future impacts.</p>
<p>To make these measurements, TeenShale Network is able to use professional scientific equipment thanks to its partnership with Earth and Environmental Systems Institute at Penn State. In return, the students provide Penn State with valuable data, which goes into a large database available to researchers.</p>
<p>“It gives you a real science experience you don’t get in the classroom,” said Alison Weiss, an eighth-grader. “I learned what it is like to take actual measurements instead of projects that have already been recorded in class.”</p>
<p>Eighth-graders like Weiss participated in the network this year for the first time. Previously, only ninth-grade students were involved. Some of those students, now in 10th grade, also returned for another year. This gives newer students the chance to learn valuable skills from their older counterparts. Also, it gives the older students the ability to teach others about what they have already learned.</p>
<p>“I’m there to point students in the right direction,” said Lena Nyblade, a 10th-grader who returned for a second year and took on a leadership role with her younger classmates. The older students have shown their classmates how to use and read equipment in the field and have gained new experience thinking about the project in a different way.</p>
<p>The younger students like eighth grader Aaron Li got a preview of the type of science they will continue to learn in high school.</p>
<p>“I wanted to increase my knowledge about the subject that I didn’t know much about before,” Li said. “I hope to get more experience in hands-on activities.”</p>
<p>In the field, Nyblade and the other 10th-graders showed their classmates how to use equipment, like the water-quality sensor called the Horiba U-53. The sensor is used to measure pH, temperature, dissolved oxygen content and other data that are indicators of the health of the stream.</p>
<p>The students also waded out into the water to use equipment called a Flow Tracker to measure the flow and depth of the creek and to collect samples to send back to Penn State for testing. Williams said they are the same types of experiments professional scientists do in the field.</p>
<p>Student said testing and sampling in the field is much different than in the classroom, where experiments often have predictable answers.</p>
<p>“In labs in class, everything is usually a lot more controlled,” Rodriguez-Hertz said. “There aren’t many variables, but here there are many variables that you have to think about.”</p>
<p>Students had to take into account things like the changing weather they experienced during their eight field trips from the fall through late April. The climate was different on each of the trips, and that greatly influenced the stream and the accessibility of the sites.</p>
<p>In the winter, deep snow covered many of the sites, and some trips had to be canceled. When the snow began to melt, the stream was very high and fast moving. Students had to consider things like whether salt added to the roads over winter would make its way into the streams and affect their data by changing electrical conductivity and chemical composition.</p>
<p>“In the classroom setting labs and activities have parameters that are predictable with some aspects of discovery,” said Phil Gipe, a ninth-grade earth science teacher. “In real life, scientific field studies, like what we’re doing here, many unknowns creep in such as logistics, supplies, organization, boots that leak, unforeseen challenges and problem solving. A project such as this really mirrors real life science in the field, science as it currently is.”</p>
<p>The students spent class time during the year analyzing and graphing their data. They presented their findings and their goals for next year at the annual Shale Network Workshop in May in State College.</p>
<p><strong><em>The writers of this article are students at State College Area High School.</em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>This article originally appeared in the Centre Daily Times.</em></strong></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>News</category>
  <category>K-12 Outreach</category>
  <category>Citizen Science</category>
  <category>Community Engagement</category>
  <guid>http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/State-High-Students-Partner-With-Penn-State-To-Monitor-Water-Quality.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.shalenetwork.org/events/State-High-Students-Partner-With-Penn-State-To-Monitor-Water-Quality/image.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
